Raphaël DERBIER

PRINCIPAL CLOUD ARCHITECT
SENIOR PRESALES
PRODUCT MANAGER
PROJECT DIRECTOR



(650) 946-8290



rderbier@gmail.com



https://rderbier.github.io



San Francisco - USA

EDUCATION

Ecole Nationale Superieure des Telecommunications, ENST (Paris, France)

Master of science Telecommunications and signal processing

CORE COMPETENCIES

Project and team lead

Problem solving

Product management

TECH COMPETENCIES

Software Engineering

Enterprise Cloud Architecture

AR VR Technologies

Graph Database

Data science and signal processing

SUMMARY

Thrive in situations where the path to success is unclear, requiring business acumen, deep technical knowledge, leadership, excellent communication, cross-team collaboration, innovation and commitment. Proven successful as technical presales in complex sales cycles for multi-million dollar deals, leader of innovation programs, cloud solution architect and software product manager in the domains of business process automation, data management and SaaS applications.

Strong technical skills nurtured by 25 years of experience in the software industry including enterprise software and cloud solution vendors.

Looking for a position where creativity, strong technical background, leadership and customer focus can make a difference.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Innovation program leader - Office of the CTO

2018-Present

TIBCO Software - Palo Alto USA

- Defined and managed products for the innovation LAB:
 - ConversationalUI: a solution to query knowledge graph databases in natural language. Inventor of pending patent on the topic.
 - Notify and GatherSmart: SaaS business applications based on AWS Serverless architecture integrated with TIBCO Cloud offering.
 - ART: first TIBCO Augmented Reality experience in Hololens integrated with enterprise data used as proof of value for marketing events.
- Managed partners relationships for the LAB: helped our partners (Intel, GigaSpaces, Advantech, ...) to create joint value propositions, proof of concepts and go-to-market strategies in data as a service (Daas) and IoT and computer vision domains.
- Acted as product evangelist for our marketing events (user conferences, webinars) and partner events.
- Supported complex sales involving product integrations and innovations.

Presales Strategic Solution Group

2013 - 2018

TIBCO Software - Palo Alto USA

- Business Process Automation and Management (BPM) Expert in the TIBCO group dedicated to complex sales and first projects implementation (Asurion, Iron Mountain, Desjardins bank, PowerSchool ...).
- Bridged the gap between engineering and customers expectations.
- Build BPM knowledge base and best practices.

EMEA Technical Presales Leader - BPM technologies

2010 - 2013

TIBCO Software - Paris France

- Covered sales cycles for BPM, SOA and B2B opportunities for 'La Banque Postale', Schlumberger,
 COFACE, BBVA, Unicredit, Vodafone Turkey), Orange, Santander, MAAF, AXA Bank Europe, AXA
 Insurance Belgium, ...
- Helped and coached solution consultants.
- Delivered first AMX BPM project on production in EMEA for AXA Bank Europe.

Consulting Department Director

2005 - 2010

Solucom - Management and IT Consulting and integration company

- Managed a team of 25 associates including developers, consultants, senior architects, team leaders.
- Responsible for business development and new projects leading to 5 M€ of annual revenue.
- Pre-sales, project leader and senior architect for various enterprise architecture projects for large customers in Finance, Transportation, Telco, Retails and Energy.

Solution architect 2001 - 2005

webMethods France - Software vendor

- Provided guidance to customers for their integration project in the area of requirement analysis,
 business modelisation, architecture, team building and training, implementation, testing, rollout and project management.
- Solved complex integration issues by providing expertise on both protocols and software development.
 Helped webMethods technical support in their understanding and resolution of customer issues.

Raphaël DERBIER 2

Dev team leader, solution architect

1996-2001

ALTEN France - Consultancy and engineering in advanced technologies.

- Designed the OS for a digital set-top box (CANAL + TECHNOLOGIES)
- Developed the embedded software of a scanner printer (SITA EQUANT)
- Designed and developed a communication software for the "Charles De Gaulle" aircraft carrier navigation system project (SAGEM)

Dev team leader 1992- 1996

VOX SA, Plessis Robinson (France) - voice processing platforms manufacturer

Led the firmware development activity.

AREAS OF EXPERTISE

Enterprise software	architected and rolled-out solutions involving BPM, analytics,
	application integration, graph databases

Project management	planning, budgeting, team leading, agile product development from
	requirements analysis to rell out

requirements analysis to roll-out.

Communication presenter in various conferences (TIBCO user conferences, Global

XR conference, BPM Summit Netherlands, XP Days France...)

Technical Presale covered all presales activities: qualifying opportunities, responding to

RFI/RFP, implementing prototypes, delivering workshops, sizing and

preparing implementation.

System architecture serverless architecture, real time for embedded systems, event

driven architecture, Object Oriented design, UML, Design patterns.

Business Knowledge acquired business knowledge through processes automation

projects in telco, retails, manufacturing, logistics, insurance and

financial services.

NLP & Graph database Named inventor in pending patent application in the field of natural

language processing for graph structure.

MISCELLANEOUS

French and American citizenships.

Bilingual French and English, notions of Spanish.

Raphaël DERBIER 3